We are starting and I hope we're live. So we're on קידושין
Kiddushin דף ו' עמוד א', Daf Vav Amud Aleph, just three lines
from the top, תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. That's where we left off,
right?
We're continuing with a number of לשונות Lashonot and testing the boundaries
as to what is an acceptable מאמר Ma'amar of קידושין Kiddushin
and we start with the following teaching: הרי את אשתי, Harei at
ishti, הרי את ארוסתי, Harei at arusati, הרי את קנויה לי. Harei
at knuya li. So he says any of those things, "you're my
wife," "you're my ארוסה," arusa, "you are קנויה knuya to me," מקודשת,
mekudeshet, that works. Further: הרי את שלי, Harei at sheli, הרי את
ברשותי, Harei at birshuti, הרי את זקוקה לי, Harei at zekuka li,
מקודשת. mekudeshet. So similarly, if he says any of those other three
לשונות, lashonot,
that also works.
Again, how to translate this, like you're mine, you're in my domain,
you're זקוקה, zekuka, these things don't necessarily have great English parallels but
you have like זיקה zika in some ways sounds like something you'd
do with a יבמה yevama but it's sort of like you're kind
of bound to me, is I guess a loose way of translating
it unless anyone has a better way of explaining it. But anyway,
so the point was this is two separate statements, right? The הרי
את מקודשת, Harei at mekudeshet, three things and you're מקודשת mekudeshet then
another three things and she's מקודשת. mekudeshet. So the גמרא Gemara asks:
וליתנינהו כולהו כחדא, V'litninhu kulhu kachada, so why not just mention it
as one big statement? Why did you divide it into two chunks?
So the answer is that that's the way he heard it, תנא
תלת שמעינהו וגריסנהו. Tana telat shmineihu v'garsineihu. That's the way he heard
it. Again, Rabbi Mizrahi I think made the point that lots of
things are grouped in groups of threes even if it's like two
things and then one thing that doesn't have anything to do with
it, they just still put it in groups of threes. I guess
that's just an easy way of remembering these types of things especially
if they have sort of a paradigm where you just make chunks
of three. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu,
so now those six לשונות lashonot worked, what about the following: מיוחדת
לי מהו? Meiyuchedet li mahu?
You're like singled out to me. מיועדת לי מהו? Meiyu'edet li mahu?
Which is again one of the לשונות lashonot of שלא יעדנה, Shelo
ya'adana, והפדה, V'hifdah, right? הבת לאמה ויעדה Habat l'amah v'ya'adah
but יעודה ye'uda is I guess literally sort of like you're designated
for me. עזרתי, Ezrati, these are all לשונות lashonot from if you
think of בראשית, Bereishit, right? עזר כנגדו, Ezer kinegdo, so if he
says עזרתי ezrati like my helpmate, נגדתי, negdati, like you'll be alongside
me. עצורתי, Atzurati,
so רש"י Rashi says that עצורה atzura as in עצרת, atzeret, which
if you look at that רש"י Rashi there שתהא נעצרת עמי לבית,
Shetihei ne'atzeret imi labayit, right? שבועות Shavuot is
like עצרת, atzeret, right? So what does עצרת atzeret mean? That like
literally if you're stopped, like you've gathered, we take this opportunity to
gather together, stay home and celebrate. So that's what in this case,
עצורתי, atzurati, like you'll be gathered together with me, I guess that's
what it's sort of saying.
צלעתי, Tzalati, ויקח אחת מצלעותיו ויסגור בשר תחתיה, Vayikach achat mitzal'otav vayisgor
basar tachtena,
God took one of the how to translate צלע, tzela, like bones
or side from אדם Adam and then ויסגור, vayasgor, he enclosed it
with flesh
and that became חוה. Chava. So what if he said צלעתי tzalati
or he said סגורתי segurati which are those לשונות lashonot from
בראשית, Bereishit,
מהו? mahu? Or תחתיי, tachtai, ויסגור בשר תחתיה, vayisgor basar tachtena, so
like under me or
תפוסתי tefusati which is like a I would think like a terrible
way of saying this with the נערה מאורסה, na'ara me'orasa,
it says והיא נתפשה v'hi nitpasha or לא נתפשה, lo nitpasha, right?
She was like seized.
But I guess if you think about it, it's like in the
context there was in a sexual context, so you're basically saying I
want to be with you that way, so presumably it means married
to me so we can be together that way. Or לקוחתי, lekuchati,
you're my taken one. What about any of that
מהו? mahu? So משום חדא, Mishum chada, we can at least answer
the last one, דתניא אומר לקוחתי הרי זו מקודשת. D'tanya omer lekuchati
harei zu mekudeshet. If we do say that last one, it totally
works, משום שנאמר כי יקח איש אשה. Mishum shene'emar ki yikach ish
isha. So that's the word that's used in the תורה Torah to
describe it, ליקוחין. likuchin. So if you say that you are taken
to me, that will work. So איבעיא להו חרופתי מהו? Iba'ya lehu
charufati mahu? Which is again like
a
form of designation but in the תורה Torah with שפחה נחרפת לאיש,
shifcha nechereset l'ish, right? That's not as much on the שפחה shifcha
as far as she's the שפחה shifcha but she's נחרפת. nechereset.
She's again however you translate this but the way this is being
translated
well actually it's not being translated. That's sort of the problem but
how it actually translates in the תורה Torah is a bit of
a debate but anyway you get the point, the point is that
she's sort of designated to somebody, נחרפת לאיש. nechereset l'ish.
So and then this guy... has relations with her. Anyway if we
say that to her does that work? Because it is only times
used I think in the context of the Torah is with a
שפחה shipchah so you know one of these transferable לשונות. leshonos. So
does it work? תא שמע Ta shema דתניא d'tanya אומר omer חרופתי
charufasi מקודשת mekudeshes it does work שכן shekein ביהודה bi-Yehuda קורין korin
לארוסה l'arusa חרופה. charufa. Because in Yehuda they call someone who's I
guess for lack of a better word like betrothed חרופה. charufa. So
the Gemara says ביהודה bi-Yehuda הויא havya לכולי עלמא l'kulei alma לא?
lo? So you say that in Yehuda so that should work everywhere
else? You know since when does the fact that they do it
in one place mean it works everywhere else? No הכי קאמר hachi
ka'amar אומר omer חרופתי charufasi מקודשת. mekudeshes. It works because of a
פסוק pasuk שנאמר shenemar והיא שפחה נחרפת לאיש ve-hi shipchah nechereset l'ish
and also ועוד ve-od ביהודה bi-Yehuda קורין korin לארוסה l'arusa חרופה. charufa.
Then the Gemara says still ועוד לקרא? ve-od l'kra? So what so
we have a פסוק pasuk and therefore we need to say oh
yeah and Yehuda too? Once you have a פסוק pasuk that's enough.
What do we really care what they do in Yehuda? So all
right let's try one more time. אלא הכי קאמר ela hachi ka'amar
אומר omer חרופה charufa ביהודה bi-Yehuda מקודשת. mekudeshes. No if you say
this לשון lashon in Yehuda itself מקודשת mekudeshes because then people know
what you mean שכן shekein ביהודה bi-Yehuda קורין korin לארוסה l'arusa חרופה.
charufa. So meaning because in Yehuda they call a ארוסה arusa חרופה
charufa and why do they do that? Probably because of the פסוק.
pasuk. But if you did that anywhere else they probably wouldn't understand
what you're saying and it probably wouldn't work. And we'll get into
that in a moment or two. So now the Gemara asks a
question: All these ambiguous לשונות leshonos not the first six which we
know work entirely but the other ones
that we had questions about like חפותי chafusi סגורתי segurasi all that
במאי עסקינן? be-mai askinan? So what kind of a case is this?
אילימא eillima בשאין be-she-ein מדבר medaber עמה imah על עסקי גיטה וקידושיה?
al iskei gitta ve-kiddusheha? If it's a case that they're not talking
about you know marriage and it throws in גיטה gitta but that
might just be because the קידושיה kiddusheha is there and also because
there's a teaching we're just going to quote in a moment so
it might just be parallel. But anyway but if they're not basically
עסוקים באותו עניין asukim be-oso inyan if they're not talking about this
מנא ידעה מאי קאמר לה? mena yada'a mai ka'amar lah? How does
she even know what he means you're my סגורתי? segurasi? I mean
you know I guess if you're very textually aware you might infer
it but they're kind of weird ways of saying it. So if
they're not talking about this stuff at all how she going to
know what he even means? And she has to you know as
opposed to a גט get which can be done בעל כורחה ba'al
korchah against her will קידושין kiddushin can't. She has to agree to
it. So if she has no idea what he's saying she's not
agreeing to it because she doesn't know what he means.
Fine ואלא ve-ela במדבר bi-medaber עמה imah על עסקי גיטה וקידושיה. al
iskei gitta ve-kiddusheha. So fine they're talking about the topic. But then
אף על גב af al gav דלא אמר לה נמי d'lo amar
lah nami but if he didn't say anything at all it's good.
So certainly if he did say something. So then what's your question
basically right? If they're not talking about what did you say? Yeah
I'm just going to say. So this guy said הרי את סגורתי
harei at segurasi or whatever it is you know and then we
want to know if it works. So the question is what is
the context? If they're not talking about קידושין kiddushin marriage related topics
then she presumably would have no idea what he means at all.
That's what the Gemara is saying. And if he is talking about
marriage related topics even if he didn't say anything he just gave
her the ring that'd be fine. So what's your question if he
says something? Either way we he doesn't have to say anything yeah
so we're just going to say that in a moment.
דתנן d'tenan היה מדבר עם אשה על עסקי גיטה וקידושיה ונתן לה
גיטה וקידושיה hayah medaber im ishah al iskei gitta ve-kiddusheha ve-nasan lah
gitta ve-kiddusheha which is why we probably said it in the very
beginning. So he's with this woman and they're talking about these types
of things גיטין gittin קידושין kiddushin cases and then he gave her
one. So if his wife he gave her the גט get or
if it was not his wife just some you know
unattached woman and he gave her
קידושין kiddushin but they're talking about the topic ולא פירש ve-lo peiraish
so he didn't you know say anything. רבי יוסי אומר דיו Rabbi
Yosei omer dayo that's good enough it works she's מקודשת. mekudeshes. ורבי
יהודה אומר צריך לפרש. ve-Rabbi Yehuda omer tzarich l'faraish. And Rabbi Yehuda
said
no no you need to say what you're doing right when you
gave her the whatever it is you know the money. I mean
it doesn't have to be a ring you know he gives her
you know five bucks and so he has to say what this
is for. ואמר רב הונא אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי. ve-amar Rav
Huna amar Shmuel halachah k'Rabbi Yosei. So and halachah is like Rabbi
Yosei and Rabbi Yosei is the one who says you don't have
to say anything. So if you don't have to say anything so
what's your question if he did say something? If he doesn't have
to say anything at all so certainly the inference is that they're
trying to establish here that if you did say something it would
be good and we know that already so what's your whole question?
So אלא ela אמרי amrei לעולם l'olam במדבר bi-medaber עמה imah על
עסקי גיטה וקידושיה. al iskei gitta ve-kiddusheha. So it had to be
a case that we are talking about על עסקי גיטה וקידושיה. al
iskei gitta ve-kiddusheha. אי דיהב לה ושתיק הכי נמי. ei d'yahiv lah
ve-shasik hachi nami. הכא במאי עסקינן דאמר לה בהני לישני. hacha be-mai
askinan de-amar lah be-hanei lishnei. So basically the point is sometimes by
saying something you make things worse. It was apparently obvious from what
you're doing then and any meaning like you're talking about it then
you give her something then it seems like the natural follow up
but if you did say something which seems weird maybe you're trying
to shift the subject especially if you said it ambiguous meaning if
you said like you know if you said like okay גיטין gittin
קידושין kiddushin say oh okay I want to go to the ball
game you know then obviously he's not trying to make So because
something that had nothing to do with any of this, okay, you
know, he buys tickets for the ballgame, you know, here's five bucks,
go online or whatever, you know, then obviously that's not, not קידושין
kiddushin by anything, that wouldn't be a question. And if he didn't
say anything, that also not be a question that, you know, okay,
you know, yes, let's get married, here's the, the ring, right? So,
but he didn't say, you know, would you, you know, be
my המקדש לי? ha-mekadesh li?
So
that, that also wouldn't be a question. But then the question is
if he does something that's neither
apparently obviously talking about something else nor does it seem like a
natural follow-up to what he's saying. He says something like, you know,
הרי את סגולתי, harei at segulati, or הרי את
כוכבתי, harei at kochavti, even better probably. Well actually no, that we
did that, he said that did work. Or anyway, one of these
other things, actually הרי את
אזמרגדי, harei at izmargadi, right? So what does that mean, right? You
know, that's why it's a question
because he said one of these things. הרי את אזמרגדי דאיכא שמא
או דילמא למלאכה קאמר לה ותיקו. harei at izmargadi de-ikka shema o
dilma limlacha ka-amar la ve-teiku. So הרי את אזמרגדי, harei at izmargadi,
right? Oh yeah, you know, like I need, you know, I have
my small medical office and I need some help, right? Maybe that's
what he means, right? So, you know, הרי את אזמרגדי, harei at
izmargadi, you know, come help in the office, you know, I need
another doctor or I need another whatever it is, you know, I
need someone to do the medical billing, you'd be great for that,
right? You know, so is he maybe that's what he means, or
no, הרי את אזמרגדי, harei at izmargadi, you know, I want you
to be my wife. So it's, it's still a little weird. I
mean, like, you know, if they were talking about it, but what
now he's suddenly talking about like work, you know, like was there
any lead-up to the work discussion? I understand if, you know, if
there's no discussion of work, then why you think maybe he means
it for work? Where did that come from? Right? So it's still
a little weird. I actually want to be something and then we'll,
we'll take your question. So and if they were talking about גיטין
וקידושין, gittin ve-kiddushin, then, you know, still seems, so it's a little
bit hard to understand. I think that, I don't know if you
have this, do you have the, the, I'm sorry there, not the
תוספות tosafot but on the side of that there's something that at
least in here תוספות הרא"ש הזקן. tosafot ha-rosh ha-zaken. Do you guys
have that? I know people who have the Artscroll have that. I
don't know if you have that over there?
Yeah, we do. Oh, you, you, use in me on
the on the left, left, left side. There's something called תוספות הרא"ש
הזקן. tosafot ha-rosh ha-zaken. Like where, see where that, I can't
look at it.
No, I think they have it there, it's like all the way
on the left. Like where you have like that sidebar there's like
a little, yeah, that. So if you go down
it's where
the the the lines get wide
and
look at למלאכה, limlacha, four lines down. It's a little small, so
you know, hopefully you can see it, but I'll read it. So
למלאכה. limlacha. So the question was does he mean that he wants
to you know take her for ארוסה arusa or wife eventually, or
does he mean he wants to you know just have her work
for him? למלאכה משמע ואף על פי ששניהם מודים שלקידושין נתכוונו. limlacha
mashma ve-af al pi she-shneihem modim she-le-kiddushin nitkavnu. But he's like,
wait and look, he you know, he's obviously wants to מקדש mekadesh
her. Just the question is you know what does he mean by
what he said, but we we know that's what he wants to
do. And let's say she says yes, yes, right you know and
and she says yeah, I thought I also wanted to I agreed,
I thought you meant that you wanted me to be my wife,
you wanted me to be your wife, and I agreed. Just say
they both say that.
עדיין אינן קידושין. adayin einan kiddushin. Why not? He says because one
thing we forget, right? We know we keep on sort of abstracting
this, we say this say that, but you know especially if you
just think about how we do it these days, what is it
done, when is it done? It's done in a room full of
people and then you actually have עדים. edim. You have עדי קידושין
edei kiddushin right? So so the his point is הרי עדים לא
נתברר להם אמיתת הלשון בעת ששמעו. harei edim lo nitbarer lahem amitat
ha-lashon be-et she-shamu. So like someone let's say you just plop somebody
in in the middle. Like they saying I guess you have to
abstract this. Is this not something that's understood between the two parties
engaging in this dialogue? But if you just plop somebody else, an
objective observer and put him there at that very moment, you know,
what would he understand what's going on? So the עדים edim heard
ואין הדבר תלוי במה שראו עדים. ve-ein ha-davar taluy be-mah she-ra-u edim.
So like the עדים, edim, you know, aren't going to necessarily understand
what's saying. He says again לא נתברר להם אמיתת הלשון. lo nitbarer
lahem amitat ha-lashon. They don't understand you know the truth of what
he's saying because like it's all in his mind. And
so therefore it's not objectively obvious, right? So it's not based on
what the עדים edim saw because they don't know what they saw.
ומסתברא אם תחילה אמרו לעדים u-mistabra im techila amru la-edim let's say
he said earlier on in the conversation הרי אני נותן לה לשם
קידושין בזה הלשון. harei ani noten lah leshem kiddushin be-zeh ha-lashon. I'm
going to מקדש mekadesh her by saying one of these things, you
know, like הרי את אזמרגדי. harei at izmargadi. והיא תאמר שתבין הלשון
שהן קידושין. ve-hi tomar she-tavin ha-lashon she-hen kiddushin. And then she also,
like so he like took them aside says you know guess what
I'm going to pop the question right? But I'm going to say
it this way.
And then later on she'll say yes I understood that's what you
meant. דודאי הוו קידושין. de-vadai havu kiddushin. Right? Then that would work.
שבשעה ששמעו עדים הלשון נתברר להם שהם קידושין. she-be-sha-ah she-shamu edim ha-lashon
nitbarer lahem she-hem kiddushin. So it's all sort of like a... In,
you know, how is it understood by an outside observer? So if
you sort of have a buildup to this situation, then,
and it was explained to an outside observer, then they would understand
it. But if there isn't, then no.
So that's basically what he says. So basically... So you're saying you
have
to be able to drop someone in the conversation and they'll understand
what's going on. He's saying the עדים edim have to have to
understand that it's קידושין kiddushin too because עדים edim are important to
קידושין. kiddushin. Right? Right, I mean it's just sort of a subtle
difference, but he's just saying everyone has to it's not just the
two of them, right? That like there's four people in a קידושין
kiddushin basically.
Right,
but let's say but I think part of the point is like
but I think it's still a bit a little bit more nuanced
because like let's say the עדים edim were there, right? And let's
say she understood it somehow, right? Why can't we just say the
עדים edim understood it just like she did? That still wouldn't work.
Meaning if he had told them before. Meaning let's say עדים edim
were there the entire conversation. You didn't ask עדים. edim. They're, you
know, you guys are there. You didn't just go, right? No, you
said, you know,
and they're עדים edim there and then they had this whole conversation
and then he said, you know, and he didn't tell them that
he was going to, you know, try to מקדש mekadesh this woman
and then he said one of these לשונות. lishonot. It still would
be a question. It would?
Yeah. And you went to everyone after?
You went to them after I think. Because, you know, just like
he said, even if he went to the woman after, she said,
yeah, I understood what he meant,
and the two עדים edim
and the two עדים edim said, yeah, it still would be a
problem because, you know, because it needs to be somehow understood by
the outside third parties. If you told them in advance and it's
understood. If you didn't. So I guess what he's saying is, so
he's sort of treading the line. I think there's some sort of
somewhat objective measure. Does that make any sense? You know, so like,
you know, so therefore it can't be totally subjective between the two
of them but they, again, the objective measure can be explained beforehand,
but you know, just this taken in isolation wouldn't be sufficient because
it's sort of unclear. That's basically what he what he says. I
don't know if that helped you at all.
At least for me it did.
Following Rabbi Yose I'm sorry?
That's Rabbi Yo so Rabbi Yose is
follow says like Rabbi... So, right, right, no but so what the
גמרא Gemara said the second before that was, yes, if he's silent
then, you know, the context would be enough, right? Because then I
guess, you know, עדים edim would understand, right? If you drop them
in at this moment, you know, they're talking about they're talking about
קידושין kiddushin and then he gives her קידושין kiddushin related stuff, right?
Then they'd understand. But if he said something a little bit off,
you know, the center there, then would an עד ed understand what
he means? Right, well no, not necessarily because like it's a weird
way of saying, you know, if you meant to say, you know,
you want to take her to whatever, why don't you say something
a little bit more direct? So maybe you're trying to things to
change the subject. So that's sort of what I got on that.
That's my way of understanding it. Let me just check something here.
Yeah, okay.
And I get to the next two dots
I'll mention a few other things.
גופא. Gufa. Go back to this. היה מדבר עם האשה על עסקי
גיטה וקידושיה. Hayah medaber im ha'ishah al iskei gitah ve'kiddusheiha.
So just like we said before, if you were talking about the
matters of marriage and divorce, ונתן לה גיטה וקידושיה, ve'natan lah gitah
ve'kiddusheiha, then you know, and he gave her the appropriate document, let's
say, or or the money for קידושין kiddushin ולא פירש ve'lo peireish
and he didn't explain anything what this was all about, רבי יוסי
אומר דיו. Rabbi Yose omer dayo. Rabbi Yose says that that's good.
רבי יהודה אומר צריך לפרש. Rabbi Yehudah omer tzarich le'fareish.
So they have to explain. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Ve'amar Rav
Yehudah amar Shmuel ומודה רבי יוסי u'modeh Rabbi Yose when did Rabbi
Yose say that this is good? והוא שעסוקין באותו ענין ve'hu she'asukin
be'oto inyan and you know, which is what we were just talking
about when they were they were talking about עסקי גיטה וקידושיה, iskei
gitah ve'kiddusheiha, meaning they still have to be talking about it, right?
So like let's say they're talking about getting married and then he
starts talking about the Yankees and, you know, then gives her money,
right, then you know, we're not so sure what that's about, right?
So even Rabbi Yose says if you don't say anything it has
to be sort of like the last thing that you did before
giving her the money or the document, whatever it is you did.
וכן אמר רב אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא והוא שעסוקין באותו ענין. Ve'chein
amar Rav Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya ve'hu she'asukin be'oto inyan.
He agrees. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, רבי אומר והוא שעסוקין
באותו ענין. Rabbi omer ve'hu she'asukin be'oto inyan. Rabbi says that yes,
they have to be talking about it. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
אף על פי שאינו עסוק באותו ענין. Rabbi Elazar be'Rabbi Shimon omer
af al pi she'eino asuk be'oto inyan. No, you don't even have
to be talking about that same matter. והגמרא שואלת ואם אינו עסוק
באותו ענין מנא ידעה דאמר לה. Ve'ha'Gemara sho'alet ve'im eino asuk be'oto
inyan mna yad'ah de'amar lah. So if they're not talking about it
anymore, then how does she know what he means when he said
whatever, you know, when he did whatever, you know, he did? אמר
אביי מתוך ענין לענין. Amar Abaye mitoch inyan le'inyan. No, I mean,
it doesn't mean you talk about something totally different, but talking about
like a related topic, right? You know, before you were talking about
literally, okay, you know, let's let's pick the let's you know, we're
going to get married, right? Then then you start talking about like,
oh yeah, you know, like oh what are your assets and you
know, what kind of dowry are you bringing in? Really, רש״י Rashi
says that, you know, then it starts, so you start talking about
not exactly you know that but peripherally the same idea. So that
would work. So that's what he means. אמר רב הונא אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rav Huna amar Shmuel halachah ke'Rabbi Yose. Basically
said before, הלכה halachah like Rabbi Yose. אמרי לה רב אמי ורב
אסי amrei lah Rav Ami ve'Rav Assi ועל הא דאמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל ve'al ha de'amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel כל שאינו יודע
בטיב גיטין וקידושין לא יהא לו עסק עמהן. kol she'eino yodeia be'tiv
gittin ve'kiddushin lo yehei lo esek imahen. So there's another statement. Ashi
eventually in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*. If somebody, you know, doesn't
really have a good understanding of גיטין Gittin. *gittin* and קידושין Kiddushin.
*kiddushin*, לא יהא לו עסק esek עמהם *lo yehei lo esek imahem*,
don't, like, you know, don't deal with it. In other words, don't
be a judge, don't be, you know, don't be involved with these,
don't be involved with things over your head basically is what he's
saying.
So who's that directed to? Is that, is that your question? דיין
בדבר *dayan bidavar* actually says, don't be a judge, right? If you're
not really like an expert in these things, you know,
just a random thought, like, you know, if you're not an expert
in these matters don't be a judge in this kind of a
case, right? Like you know say you need to go to בית
דין *beis din* and do whatever it is, you know, don't be
on that בית דין *beis din*. So he says, okay, so, so
there was that statement. So
again if you're not a thorough expert on that, don't be involved.
אפילו שלא יהא לך הא דרב הונא אמר שמואל *afilu shelo yehei
lecha hada de'Rav Huna amar Shmuel*, even if you don't know that
הלכה Halacha. *halacha* of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*, right? Because שמואל *Shmuel*
said the הלכה *halacha* is like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*. And רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* says if you're talking about גיטין Gittin. *gittin* and
קידושין Kiddushin. *kiddushin* then just give her something, you didn't say what
it is you're doing when you're giving it to her, that's good
enough. So if you don't know that הלכה *halacha*, is that also
considered that you're sufficiently ignorant of הלכות *halachot* of גיטין *gittin* and
קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin* and therefore you should not sit on a בית
דין *beis din*? Even something I guess as obscure as that, if
you don't know that law would you still, you know, be considered
unknowledgeable in that area? אמר ליה אינך הכי נמי *amar leh ein
hach nami* yes. That's right. Even if you don't know that הלכה
*halacha* then
I wouldn't suggest that you be part of this בית דין *beis
din*. So that's what he's saying.
And you know the other day we talked about
remember we talked about
if you give her
a loan oh no that's going to be something a little later
so you know I'll wait until we get up to that. Fine.
Never mind. וכן בגירושין נתן לה גיטה ואמר לה הרי את משולחת
הרי את מגורשת הרי את מותרת לכל אדם הרי היא מגורשת *vechen
bigirushin natan lah gita ve'amar lah harei at meshulachet harei at megureshet
harei at muteret lechol adam harei hi megureshet*. So we now before
we just talked about what potentially would or wouldn't be
a good לשון *lashon* of קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin*. Now on the back
end if you're getting divorced and then you give her the גט
*get* and then you said הרי את משולחת *harei at meshulachet* or
מגורשת *megureshet* or מותרת לכל אדם *muteret lechol adam*, those are good.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פשיטא *pshita* it's obvious to
us. נתן לה גיטה *natan lah gita* gave her the גט *get*
אמר לה לאשתו *amar lah leishto* הרי את בת חורין *harei at
bat chorin*, you're free, right? Which is really a לשון *lashon* that
you say for a slave, right? You're free. לא אמר ולא כלום
*lo amar velo klum*. You didn't say anything. That's not, you know,
again remember we said the ספר כריתות *sefer kraitut* that the ספר
*sefer* itself has to be obvious and also when you give it
to her you know it kind of has to be understood that
that's what you're giving it to her for. So you didn't say
that, that doesn't work. אמר לשפחתו הרי את מותרת לכל אדם *amar
leshifchato harei at muteret lechol adam*. So basically you reversed languages. You
said to your wife something you'd say to your slave and you
said to your slave something you'd say to your wife. אמר לשפחתו
הרי את מותרת לכל אדם *amar leshifchato harei at muteret lechol adam*.
You said you are מותרת *muteret* for anybody, right? No, but when
you free a slave you don't say you're מותרת *muteret* for anyone
you say you're free, right? הרי את בת חורין *harei at bat
chorin*. So you switched the לשונות *leshonot*.
In that case also לא אמר ולא כלום *lo amar velo klum*.
It doesn't mean anything. Maybe he had both a wife and a
slave but you know he just said the wrong thing to the
wrong person. So that doesn't count either. But what about one of
these ambiguous cases? Again the same idea that we had before regarding
the קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* now we're having for the גירושין *gerushin*. You
said הרי את לעצמך Harei at le'atzmekh. *harei at le'atzmech*, you're you
know alright you're for yourself. מהו
*mahu*?
So what does that mean? מי אמרינן למלאכה קאמר או דלמא לגמרי
קאמר *mi amrinan lemlacha ka'amar o dilma legamrei ka'amar*? Does it mean
you're free to go, right?
Like you know now you're by yourself, in other words we're not
attached anymore, I'm divorcing you. Or does it mean no you're הרי
את לעצמך *harei at le'atzmech* you get to keep your מעשה ידיה
*ma'aseh yadecha*? Because you know we have the husband the whole deal
is because he supports her then he gets to keep the you
know the fruits of her labor and stuff like that. So maybe
you're saying alright fine you know I'm not going to support you
but you can keep whatever you know you can keep all the
profits from your business. So he says is that what he means
or is he mean to divorce her? So that's the question when
he says הרי את לעצמך *harei at le'atzmech*. What does he mean
by that? אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי תא שמע דתניא *amar leh
Ravina le'Rav Ashi ta shma detanya* and then we're going to bring
a proof that we had learned already in the prior מסכת *masechet*
דתניא גופו של גט שחרור Get Shichrur *detanya gufo shel get shichrur*.
And we learn a lot from גיטי נשים *gitei nashin* and גיטי
עבדים *gitei avadim* like גט שחרור shichrur. *get shichrur* to a גט
*get* of a woman. So how does it work by freeing a
slave? הרי אתה בן חורין הרי אתה לעצמך *harei ata ben chorin
harei ata le'atzmecha*. So you're free, you're for yourself. And this is
what you say for a slave. So now they're going to try
to make a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. השתא מה עבד כנעני Eved
Kena'ani, דקני ליה לגופיה *hashta mah eved kena'ani dekani lei legufei*, that
you own him for his body because you really own him. כי
אמר ליה הרי אתה לעצמך לגמרי קאמר *ki amar lei harei ata
le'atzmecha legamrei ka'amar*. So when you're saying you're for yourself you know
it means entirely for yourself and it doesn't mean that you know
now okay you like have a side business and you know you
can keep whatever you know profits you make from your little business
there. Since you own him entirely and it means that you are
free entirely.
אישה דלא קני ליה לגופיה *isha dlo kani lei legufei*, you don't
own
your wife. So when you say that לא כל שכן *lo kol
sheken*? Then certainly it means that it certainly means that you go
free entirely. So the point is, so certainly, you know, you mean
from one case that's super extreme, you can interpret it to be
more narrow.
She's entirely, or he's entirely free, the עבד, so certainly with the
wife, it means that no, you know, it doesn't mean the הלכה.
You didn't say that there, we're not going to say that here.
Okay, I mean one we
had
in גיטין.
Yeah, yeah, exactly, that's what I'm saying. This is a repeat from,
so and it's like that to the two dots, so a few
more lines. איבעיא להו דאשכחיה אמר לעבדו אין לי עסק בך מאי
Iba'ya lehu: de'ash'chei amar le'avdo 'ein li esek bakh', mai?
So now you know, alright now we're talking about a slave. Let's
say he said to his slave, "I have nothing more to do
with you, we're done." מי אמרינן אין לי עסק בך לגמרי קאמר
או דלמא למלאכה קאמר Mi amrinan 'ein li esek bakh' legamrei ka'amar,
o dilma lamlakhah ka'amar? Does it mean alright, now we're like, you're
free, you know, I really have nothing to do with you and
you know, you're out of my, out of my domain? Or
does it mean no, you know, I don't have anything to do
with your, you know, your work, but you know, you're still... I
mean, he didn't free him entirely, but you know, this guy can,
you know, work for himself now.
Because again, like you know, freeing is not just a matter of
work, it's also a matter, especially עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani it's a
matter of status, right? If you free him, then it becomes, you
know, basically ישראל. Yisrael. So if you don't free him, he's not,
you know, fully Jewish, so to speak.
So what does he mean by that? אין לי עסק בך. Ein
li esek bakh. Is it in a narrow sense regarding work or
is it in a more broader sense, now he's free?
So and again, this is, we had this
in גיטין. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב אשי
ואמרי לה רב חנין מחוזאה לרב אשי תא
שמע מוכר עבדו לעובד כוכבים יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור מרבו ראשון
Amar leih Rav Nachman le-Rav Ashi, va'amri lah Rav Chanin me-Chuza le-Rav
Ashi: Ta shma, mokher avdo le-oveid kokhavim, yatzah le-cheirut ve-tzarikh get shichrur
me-rabo rishon. So he does go free, but he still needs this
document to back it up from the guy who's selling him, you
know, the Jewish guy who's selling him to the non-Jew.
Why does he go free? Because you know, again, he's considered מופקע
ממצוות, mufka mi-mitzvot, you know, that whole thing. But that's not... anyway,
the point is, you need a גט שחרור and, but רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says במה דברים אמורים שלא כתב
עליו אונו be-mei devarim amurim? she-lo katav alav ono. If you at
the time didn't write אונו. ono. אבל כתב עליו אונו זהו שחרורו
Aval katav alav ono, zehu shichruro.
But if you wrote this אונו, ono, then that is a שטר
שחרור, Shtar Shichrur, you don't need to go then and write an
official one. היכי דמי אונו אמר רב ששת דכתב ליה כשתברח ממני
אין לי עסק בך Heichi dami ono? Amar Rav Sheshet: dikatav leih
'kshe-tivrakh mimeni, ein li esek bakh'. When you if you, you know,
run away from me, I have nothing to do with you. So
clearly you mean, so if you write this אונו, ono, then it's,
then that already considers a שטר שחרור. Shtar Shichrur. So that answers
the question. The question was, if you say אין לי עסק בך,
ein li esek bakh, do you go free? The answer is yes,
because if you wrote this אונו, ono, which is "I have no
עסק for you", that's considered שחרור. So that's the answer.
Okay.
Now going back to
קידושין. We're done with the digression of slaves.
What did he say about if he says,
"You are unto yourself" to a... it says it's a valid divorce,
right?
הרי את לעצמך.
Yeah, but is it also valid for freeing the slave?
Yeah, I mean that's the... I think that's the illustration, right? Because
you said that if you have, if you say that by עבד
כנעני Eved Kena'ani, and proof was from an עבד כנעני, if you
say "You are for yourself", that is considered a, you know, way
of freeing. So certainly if you say that to your wife, that's
a way of freeing. And then the only question was what about
if you say something else, like you are,
you
say
right, and we said that yes, basically. So
okay, so אמר אביי, amar Abaye, now this is, this is kind
of interesting. So how much does the object that you give, let's
say we're talking about money, right? Because that's what we usually do
for קידושין. So how much yours does the object have to be?
Like, is it fully yours, personal, or what do we mean by
that?
And how much hers does it have to be? So like let's
say I borrow something from you, then I, you know, say, oh,
you know, that car that I borrowed from you, like you know,
I borrow something from you, and then I give it to a
woman, can I be מקדש mekadesh with a borrowed car? Is it
considered mine? That we won't talk about, but let's say the other
way around. Let's say she borrowed something, you know, then
you're מקדש mekadesh that with her. In other words, let's say she
borrowed a hundred bucks from me and I say, "Alright, with that
hundred bucks that you borrowed, you're מקודשת mekudeshet to me." She has
to pay back, right? So did you give her anything? You know,
or let's say even something more intangible. We're going to get with
these kind of things. Let's say we talk about הנאה, hana'ah, right?
You are מקודשת mekudeshet to me by the הנאה hana'ah that whatever.
We'll talk about it right now. So anyway, but the point is,
so how...
money is tangible, right? But if it's going to go back, is
that considered giving her anything? And then let's say something entirely intangible
like הנאה. hana'ah. And we're going to start talking about that now.
It's going to be a pretty big topic.
אמר אביי המקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת בהנאת מלווה מקודשת אבל אסור לעשות
כן מפני הערמת ריבית Amar Abaye: hamikadesh be-malveh, einah mekudeshet. be-hana'at malveh,
mekudeshet, aval asur la'asot kein mipnei ha'aramat ribit. So this is all
going to be explained, I'll just like literally translate it, but I
won't explain it because the גמרא Gemara is going to do that.
So if you're מקדש mekadesh somebody with a loan,
then that doesn't work. So like you know, alright, with the hundred
bucks that I gave... I want you to be מקודשת mekudeshet to
me. That doesn't work.
But if you do it בהנאת מלווה, bahana'at malveh, it would work,
but you shouldn't do it because it sort of like smacks of
ריבית. ribit. I'll explain it in just a second, but let's just
wait another line, gives you that?
No, I was just going to say, we're saying that the loan
is definitely something that the
money that the woman owes him, not money that someone else owes?
Yeah, that we're saying is the money the woman owes him. Yeah.
So now and I'm going to go back and explain it במלווה
bemalveh too. So הנאת מלווה, hana'at malveh, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what
does that mean הנאת מלווה? hana'at malveh? What does that mean? אילימא
eileima דאזקפה de'azkafa דאמר לה de'amar lah ארבע
בחמש. arba bechamesh. So let's say he said, okay, listen, I'm going
to give you back, I'm sorry, I'm going to loan you a
hundred bucks, but you're going to give me back a hundred and
twenty five bucks, right? That's what, that was the terms of the
loan. That's what he did. And then he says, you know, the
twenty five bucks you're going to give me, it's okay, you know,
don't give it back, but I want you to be מקודשת mekudeshet
to me for that, for those, you know, twenty five bucks, right?
So that's what he means by that, like ארבע בחמש. arba bechamesh.
What do you mean like it's worth, but it's like you can't
do it because it sort of looks like ריבית, ribit, but it
isn't really? It is ריבית, ribit, right? So the גמרא's Gemara saying
it sort of looks like ריבית. ribit. No, it's really
ריבית, ribit, right? דהיינו מלווה, dehayeinu malveh, then that's actually, that's not
הנאת מלווה, hana'at malveh, that is the loan, right? So it can't
be that that's what we're talking about. No, לא צריכא דארבח לה
זימנא. lo tzricha de'arvach lah zimna. So it means that
he
extended the time. He says, alright, you're going to pay me back
Thursday, you're going to pay me back today, I'll let you pay
me back a month from now. So the הנאה hana'ah that you
get to have the money for longer, I want you to be
מקודשת mekudeshet to me. So that would actually work, but you can't
do it because it smacks of ריבית. ribit. So let's explain this
a little bit. So let's just go back for a moment and
say what the, let's look at the actual loan case. אינה מקודשת.
eina mekudeshet. So look at, look at רש״י, Rashi, המקדש במלווה, hamakadesh
bemalveh, it's really sort of hard for me to explain where that
is, but if you have ליקוטי רש״י Likkutei Rashi on the left
hand side, it's like six lines into it on the, you know,
in רש״י, Rashi, but starting from where ליקוטי רש״י Likkutei Rashi is,
if you have that, in at least an ArtScroll that's the way
it is, but if you're not on ArtScroll, it's narrow lines, you
know, whatever, like
two-fifths of the way down. If you see it, you see it,
I mean it's sort of hard, like המקדש במלווה. hamakadesh bemalveh.
Just look at, do you see המקדש במלווה? hamakadesh bemalveh? He said
דאמר התקדשי לי במלווה שיש לי בידיך,
de'amar
hitkadshi
li bemalveh sheyesh li beyadeich, so that's your answer to your question.
You're... התקדשי? hitkadshi?
Yes, I've already, right? So there's going to be a lot of
questions, which let's say he doesn't right now, but we'll see, like
I'll be a little cagey because I want, I want us to
like see what רש״י Rashi says and then sort of try to
infer a few things. So
I've already loaned you a hundred bucks, right? So now he comes
to her a few days later, that's he says the case is.
So it's actually not as much I'm loaning you a hundred bucks
now, I want you to be מקודשת mekudeshet to me for the
money that you know, whatever, for the twenty five, whatever it is,
right? Like we said before, like I've loaned you a hundred dollars,
you're going to give back twenty five, a hundred and twenty five,
that you know, that wasn't even our case, or it doesn't say
okay, I'm loaning you now a hundred bucks, it's due in a
week from now, but you know,
I'm going to reconsider that and you know pay me back further
out, that's not the case. The case is you already loaned it
to her. And then he said, alright, you know, you're going to
pay me back, you know, next Thursday, you know, pay me back
whatever, you know, a month later.
So why not, אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshet, דקיחה מידי עפרון גמרינן דייהב
מידי בשעת קידושין, dekicha mi'dei Efron gamrinan deyahav mi'dei bish'at kiddushin, right?
So again, our model, at least the, the money part was learned
from עפרון Efron and עפרון, Efron, אברהם Avraham gives to עפרון Efron
at that time money, right? And you know, of course it's like
he gives it to him, it's not like he didn't loan it
to him, he gave it to him. So at the time he
gave him money. But however a loan is different, דהוצאה ניתנה, dehotza'ah
nitnah, כבר הן שלה, kevar hein shela, it's already hers. In other
words, yes, it's her she has to pay him back, so it's
not necessarily it's, but it's hers, right? So it's not his anymore.
He can't מקדש, mekadesh, it's sort of like, you know, and I
sort of, I like to say this
to my kids a lot because like, let's say you give a,
for in general, you give someone like a present, right? And you
didn't specify like I'm giving it to you to use for this.
And then you say, like, but I didn't want you to use
it for that, you know, I wanted, no no, I only gave
you that toy so you can play it with me, or I
want you, you know what I mean? That's not, no, you give
a gift, you know, you tell them they can do this, that's
it. It's not your money anymore. It's not your gift anymore. It's
not your whatever it is. It's theirs for the time being. Right?
Like I think that's a very important point, you know, at least
that I try to tell my kids, you know, you can't keep
on putting strings, no strings attached, right? If you're going to give,
then give something. I mean unless at the time, you know, you
made a specific condition. Alright, that's something else. But you can't just
go change the parameters now, right? So it's not his anymore. He
doesn't have control over it. You know, she has to pay him
back, yeah, I understand, but like but so he's not מקדש mekadesh
her, he's not giving her anything anymore so to speak. It's already
is hers.
He owes her 100 dollars, not these 100 dollars. So what money
is like gone, right? So he wasn't מקדש mekadesh her with anything.
Okay so now what was the problem in the other case of
he extended the time, right?
That so why did it work and what would be the problem
of ריבית? ribit? So it works because this is what רש"י Rashi
says, it's interesting explanation.
הלוואת זמן halva'at zeman that's a few lines down from where I
ended off that prior רש"י. Rashi.
So he protracted the time
לא דאצטריכא דארווח לה זימנא. lo de-itztricha de-arvach lah zimna. That's that
רש"י. Rashi. He extended the time frame for payback and אמר לה
התקדשי לי בהנאה זו שאת היית נותנת פרוטה לאדם שיפייסני עליך. amar
lah hitkadshi li be-hana'ah zu she-at hayit notenet perutah le-adam she-yefayeseni alayich.
So now he's saying ah, okay. So it's money really because you
would have paid somebody a פרוטה perutah
to, you know, approach me or you would have been willing, if
you, you know, not necessarily, you theoretically would have been willing to
pay somebody a פרוטה, perutah, like a, you know, small but
not you know, completely insignificant amount of money to approach me to
extend the time frame for repayment. Right, so with that money that
you're quote-unquote saving, I'm
מקדש mekadesh you, right? So that's what that is.
So
it's הנאת ריבית. hana'at ribit. דהוה ליה לאו ריבית גמור. de-hava leh
lav ribit gamur. Why is it not ריבית גמור? ribit gamur? We're
not going to get into so much about ריבית ribit as right
now. דלא קטלה מידי ולא מידי שקל מינה de-lo katla midei velo
midei shakal minah because he didn't actually take anything from her. He's
not getting anything from her so he's not actually getting ריבית, ribit,
right? You know, if you actually got that extra, if you actually,
you know, if I really, I loaned you 100 dollars, I get
back 101, that's ריבית. ribit. But here he did not get anything.
So it's not full ריבית ribit but somewhat to be he's getting
something out of it, right? He's getting a wife, right? So he's
getting something out of it.
So it works but you shouldn't do it because it sort of
looks like ריבית, ribit, right? Because you're getting something out of it.
You know, the idea is you give somebody a loan and that's
the end of it. Jewishly, right, you're not supposed to take ריבית.
ribit. היתר עיסקא Heter Iska is a whole other story. But you
give 100 dollars, you get back 100 dollars. That's it, right? Here
you're getting something more, right? You're getting the wife out of this.
Now he says וכל שכן אם מחלה כל המלווה. ve-kolsheken im machala
kol ha-malveh. Right, so he said forget, forget the hundred, forget the
extra dollar that you would have been willing to pay me, right?
That's like above and beyond the loan. And forget the fact that
you know, that
that I loaned you 100 you give back 125. That's really ריבית.
ribit. But let's say you said, alright, I loaned you 100 dollars,
I already loaned you 100 dollars. I'm going to forgive the loan,
right? Would that work if if
like he forgives the loan entirely? Not that he's giving her the
added benefit of repaying it later but he forgives, you know, no
added benefit to the loan but he cancels the loan. Right? הרי
את מקודשת לי בהנאת מחילה זו דהשתא הוא דקייא ולאו אפשטא דאת
מלווה. harey at mekudeshet li be-hana'at mechilah zu de-hashta hu de-kaya ve-lav
afshata de-at malveh. Right?
Then that would work, that would work. Because now he's actually giving
her a benefit, right? אבל נתקדשה בעיקר מעות ולא מידי יהיב לה
שכבר היו ברשותה והם שלה.
aval nitkadsha be-ikkar ma'ot
velo midei yahiv lah she-kevar hayu birshuta ve-hem shela.
In other words, it's sort of like view it like this: if
he cancels a loan, right, he's giving something new now. But, but,
if he says, but beforehand, when he
when he does these things we said במלווה, be-malveh, that,
that
you know, that then we had our other problems that you know,
that the money was already hers. So it's a little bit ambiguous,
so let's let's go into let's let's try to explain this a
little bit more. So I have from my my my notes over
here that so the הראש ha-Rosh agrees with this
that extending the time of
of the loan is you know, is you're basically מקדש mekadesh her
with the monetary value of of things. That and
and so
they basically they say that הנאת מלווה hana'at malveh is that you
extended the the time frame but it actually is not as it's
לאו דווקא lav davka because really it'd be as he just said
a second ago that הנאת מלווה hana'at malveh
is also that you מקדש mekadesh her with the מחילה mechilah
of the whole loan, right? So it works either way. So
that that would work. But the הר"ן ha-Ran says that's actually you
really mean that, that that it means that you extended the time
but if you wanted to actually forgive the whole loan that wouldn't
work, that wouldn't work.
For partly the same reason we said before, because like you know,
the money was already given, right, and that’s the end of it,
you know, and now she’s not actually she’s not actually thinking now
of,
you have to מקדש mekadesh her with something new. Something new could
be the הנאה hana'ah she gets from, you know, whatever it is.
Right? But now she’s not thinking about the extra הנאה hana'ah that
she’s getting, she’s thinking about the actual money at the time, the
money that was given before. So she’s like thinking about the hundred
bucks, not the extra, not the new benefit of having
הנאה hana'ah of... is that still a little complicated? In other words,
you have to מקדש mekadesh her with something that wasn’t there, something
now. Right? The something now could be the הנאה hana'ah she gets
from not having to do something, right, or for having further timeframes.
Right? So of course, well, if extra timeframe is good,
then not paying anything back is entirely good. No, but the ר"ן
Ran says no, that’s not true.
There’s not... forgiving the loan is not, quote-unquote, something new. 400 bucks
was already there. Right? You have to מקדש mekadesh her with something
above and beyond that, so to speak. So the ר"ן Ran would
disagree with רש"י Rashi over there.
So now partly the question would also be,
let’s say,
does it make a difference when you said this? Right? In other
words, let’s say it was money you gave her. Is there and
say alright, you’re going to pay me next Thursday, whatever. But do
you have to do that like on that Thursday? Right? Do you
have to come, then it’s like, then it’s something new or, you
know, then it’s like sort of like more in your mind and
tangible, quote-unquote tangible? Or can it be like even, you know, if
there’s a lot of time? Right? You know, it was a 15-year
loan, right? And then, you know, then two days into it, and
alright, don’t pay me back in 15 years, pay me back 15
years and a day, right? Is that really
helpful? Right? So you know, so some say maybe not. You know,
it might depend like if you’re already approaching the time of payment,
then there’s like, then you really feel הנאה, hana'ah, right?
So that, that would work, but not necessarily if you jump the
gun on this. So and also like there are other ways the
רשב"א Rashba mentions the point, that if it’s towards the end of
the loan,
then because then you have the כל העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי, kol
ha'omed ligbot kegavuy dami, those are other principles, if it’s ready to
be
collected,
it’s as if it’s collected and therefore he can מקדש mekadesh her
with this extra time because like, you know, then he’s given her
something, but if it was not ready to be collected then doing
that wouldn’t work at all.
So that might be a further nuance as to הנאת מלוה. hana'at
malveh. It might depend when you do it. Right? Because then the
closer when it’s due to be repaid, then it’s in your power
to extend it so to speak and that’s הנאה hana'ah you’re really
giving to her because it’s yours now. But if
it’s beforehand then it’s still too abstract,
right, to work. Now the final question would be like again רש"י
Rashi was very insistent that, you know, he turned this הנאה hana'ah
to something concrete, right? Like you know I'm מקדש mekadesh you with
the פרוטה perutah that you would have paid somebody else to have
extended the loan. Right? But let’s say you didn’t say that. Just
I'm מקדש mekadesh you with the הנאה hana'ah that you got from
having this loan or whatever it is, you know, would that work?
So some people say, you know, or the הנאה hana'ah that you
have for just like feeling more secure, right? Not the money you
would have paid to approach someone to, you know, now that you
have an extra day, you know, you don’t have to like, I
saved you the trip to go to the ATM, you know? Like
that’s, you know what I mean? It didn’t cost her money but
it like cost her inconvenience. Right? Would that be a valid form
of קידושין? That might be a separate question.
Okay.
So those are some of the notes I have on this subject.
I mean I have a lot more notes but I’m not going
to go into it. So I just want to finish the דף.
daf. So okay, just a few more minutes. אמר רבא: Amar Rava:
הילך מנה על מנת שתחזירהו לי. heilech maneh al menat shetachzirehu li.
So sort of like you know when you give the לולב lulav
in סוכות, Sukkot, right? Here’s the לולב lulav but you got to
give it back to me. Right? Does that work in the case
of במכר לא קנה באשה אינה מקודשת בפדיון הבן אין בנו פדוי
אבל בתרומה יצא ידי נתינה ואסור לאכלה משום דקיימא ליה בטובת הנאה.
bemecher lo kanah beishah einah mekudeshet bepidyon haben ein beno paduy aval
biterumah yatza yedei netinah veasur leochlah mishum dekaima lei betovat hanaah. What
does all this mean? So different cases. So here’s the hundred bucks
but you got to give it back to me. So if this
is a sale, right? I’m paying you a hundred bucks for your
car but you got to give it back to me. Right? So
that’s not a sale. Right?
Isn’t that similar to extending a loan? I mean in essence because
you’re saying I’m giving you something for a short period of time
and eventually you’re going to
have to give it back to you. Well it’s not extending, no
here he said give, like let’s say it’s instantaneous. Here’s a hundred
bucks, give it back to me right now. No, I mean, I
get that it’s a different situation but I’m saying like in the
realm of trying to understand I don’t know like the... Isn't that
similar to extending a loan? I mean, in essence, because you're saying
I'm giving you something for a short period of time and eventually
you're going to give it back to me. But it's not extended.
No. Here he said, let's say it's instantaneous. Here's your משכון Mashkon
back to her right now.
Right. I
mean,
I get that
it's a different situation, but I'm saying in
the realm of trying to understand—I don't know—the—but this is a new
רישא, Reisha, though, by the way. But I'm just saying I feel
like there's—I don't know—it's weird to me that one would work and
one wouldn't.
Well, again, because the way I was trying to say is extending
the loan is now giving her a new הנאה. Hana'ah. Right? That,
in other words, she thought originally, okay, loan is for five days,
and now it's ten days. Oh, okay, that's something new; that wasn't
there now. But you're just saying, here's a loan, right? I mean,
it's not even a loan; like,
it could be a loan, but like, you know, here's a hundred
bucks, give it back to me. Like מתנה על מנת להחזיר, Matanah
al menat lehachzir, right? So is that working? There's nothing extended; it's
just you're trying to do it with the גוף Guf of the
whatever. So I'm trying to buy something from you, but I'm not
really paying you, right? So obviously, so if it's a sale, it's
not a good sale. I mean, is that making any sense? If
it's a sale, it's not a good sale. בשן וקדשה, Bishan vekiddeshah,
with a woman,
she's not מתקדשת. mitkadeshet. בפדיון
הבן, Bifidyon haben, if you give the כהן Kohen five סלעים Sela'im
but you say, 'All right, you gotta give it back to me,
buddy,' you know, it's not considered a good פדיון. Pidyon. But
בתרומה, Bitrumah,
like if I say to the
כהן, Kohen, 'Here's your תרומה, trumah, give it back to me,' right?
יצא ידי נתינה. Yatza yedei netinah. That's actually good. But ומסלעותו דכהן
משמי דכהן מסייעא בבית הגנואת. Umisla'uto deKohen mishmei deKohen hamesaye'a beveit haganvat.
It looks like the guy's helping you. What does that mean? Meaning
like there's an עניין Inyan of תרומה, trumah, like the תרומה trumah
is supposed to be a gift, right? God just gives it to
the כהנים; Kohanim; it's their gift. They don't have to do anything
for it, so to speak—I mean, well, ultimately they are, because they're
working in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and they're, you know, helping
effectuate the כפרה Kapparah of בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. But it looks
like—it looks too like you're having too close a relationship; it's like
you're buying him, right? In other words, what's going to happen? You
say, 'All right, this תרומה, trumah, I really, you know, don't need
this today,' you know, 'like I don't want to give it to
you. So take it, give it back,' right? So and then, you
know, then now I'm gone, now I can eat my whatever, right?
But it looks like then you're sort of ערמה Armah out. Because
like a כהן Kohen can't help—let's say the כהן Kohen says, 'All
right, I'll go help you with your harvest, right, but you give
me your תרומה.' trumah. Then it looks like he bought the תרומה,
trumah, right? Even if the guy would have given it to him
anyway, but like, you know, if you have the כהן Kohen working
in the—oh yeah, these guys are too tight, you know, all the
כהנים Kohanim are going to say, 'All right, I have no way
of, you know, getting in there.' He bought them with his—you know,
with his work. So you're not allowed to do that with
תרומה. trumah. And in this case, too, if you're going to take
it and give it back, it looks like, you know, you've made
some sort of relationship there. You've made a deal. You're like, you
know, back-dealing with תרומה. trumah. So they don't want that; it's sort
of like a בזיון Bizayon for תרומה. trumah. So it looks like
that if you're מתנה על מנת להחזיר. Matanah al menat lehachzir. But
it works, though. I mean, they don't want you doing it, right?
But it does, you know, you have actually fulfilled your obligation to
give תרומה. trumah. Whereas if you tried to do that for קידושין,
let's say, it doesn't work at all. It's not like we say
it works but don't do it, right? It just doesn't work. So
then the question is, well, make up your mind, right? Why is
the כהן Kohen case any different? Why are you saying it works
but don't do it, whereas the other ones you're saying it doesn't
work at all? Right? If it works, it works; if it doesn't,
it doesn't. That's basically the גמרא is trying to say, all or
nothing.
So מאי קסבר רב אשי? Mai kasavar Rav Ashi? אי קסבר מתנה
על מנת להחזיר שמה מתנה, Ei kasavar matanah al menat lehachzir shemah
matanah, ובתרומה נמי, Uvitrumah nami, if you really believe me giving a
gift that has to be, you know, repaid, so to speak—not repaid,
given back, right—is considered a good gift, then all the rest should
work. It should work by פדיון, Pidyon, should work by woman, you
know, should be considered, you know, you gave money for the sale.
And also,
I'm sorry, and ואי קסבר לא שמה מתנה, Ve'ei kasavar lo shemah
matanah, ובתרומה נמי לא, Uvitrumah nami lo, if it doesn't work, then
why does it work by תרומה? trumah? You said it works, but
don't do it, right? So it shouldn't work for that. ורבא איהו
דאמר מתנה על מנת להחזיר שמה מתנה. Verava ihu de'amar matanah al
menat lehachzir shemah matanah. And Rava, you yourself hold that it works.
So
if
it does work, then they should all work, right? And how do
we know it works? דאמר רבא הילך אתרוג זה על מנת שתחזירהו
לי. De'amar Rava heilach etrog zeh al menat shetachzirehu li. In the
סוכות Sukkot case, right? Here, you know,
I know you need to—you need to bench לולב Lulav and אתרוג.
Etrog. Go ahead, take mine but give it back to me, right?
נטלו והחזירו יצא. Netalo vehachziro yatza.
You give it back, it works. ואם לאו לא יצא. Ve'im lav
lo yatza. If you didn't, you didn't fulfill your obligation. So which
is it? Right? In other words, basically it should be all or
nothing, right? And the way we're saying it, Rava holds שמה מתנה,
Shemah matanah, it should be all. So תרומה trumah should work; we
understand that, because it works. What about all the other cases? Why
do you say in the other cases it does not work? אלא
אמר רב אשי. Ella amar Rav Ashi. You got the גרסא Girsa
wrong. It does all work. בכולהו קני. Bechulehu kani. In all these
cases. But לבר מאשה. Levar me'ishah. So פדיון הבן Pidyon haben it
works, for מכר Mecher it works, for תרומה trumah it works—we don't
want you doing it for תרומה trumah for other reasons, but it
works—but woman, it does not work. It doesn't work for קידושין, בשאין
אשה נקנית בחליפין. She'ein ishah nikneit bachallipin. Because, you know, there's a
certain way—like
you
have to, you know, you have to give something, and, you know,
as we learned from שדה עפרון, Sedei Ephron, it wasn't a חליפין.
Challipin. סודר וחליפין Sudar vechallipin are sort of the same idea, right?
Like, in other words, like how does it work for
פסח? Pesach? I grab the other guy's handkerchief, whatever, let's say whatever
it is, right? He gives me—I take his handkerchief, and in exchange
I give him my חמץ, Chametz, right? And then he, you know,
he—and it's now in his power to sell it to, you know,
whoever it is, John Smith, right?
So it looks either is חליפין Challipin or it looks too much
like חליפין Challipin in this case by a woman. In other words,
with the סודר, Sudar, the classic case is, you know, you hold
on—as even the rabbis have mentioned, even the rabbi can even potentially
be holding... On to the סודר sudar at the same time. He
takes it, it's like instantaneous, he takes it and he gets it
right back, right? So with the סודר, sudar, right? So I get
it and he gets it right back. I don't keep his wallet,
you know if he's using the wallet, I don't keep his handkerchief.
He, the rabbi, gets it right back. So but with a woman
you have to give something. So if you say
that here's the money, give it back to me, then that's like
a חליפין chalupin essentially and it doesn't work. But if you think
of the אברהם Avraham model, אברהם Avraham gives עפרון Ephron the money
and that's the end of it, right? He doesn't get it back.
So it doesn't work because אין אשה נקנית בחליפין. ein isha nikneit
b'chalupin. אמר ליה רב הונא Amar lei Rav Huna אמר ליה רב
amar lei Rav רב Rav נחמיה דרב אשי Nechemia d'Rav Ashi הכי
אמינא משמיה דרבא כוותיך. hachi amina mishme d'Rava k'vaysaich. Yeah, yeah, yeah,
you got the גרסא girsa right. It wasn't what we said before,
that
the three don't work but תרומה terumah does. No, it's that,
meaning it's that
they all work except for the woman one. Meaning that תרומה terumah
worked, don't do it, the
מכר mecher works and פדיון הבן pidyon haben works, but the woman
thing does not because it looks or is, you know, either looks
like people will think that it's חליפין chalupin or it is a
חליפין, chalupin, whatever it is, it just doesn't work. So and that's
the right גרסא girsa to be operating on here. All right, so
we will end here. Thanks Mike.
Yes sir. These are
worn out.